Guide to the Flora Moon Papers
Flora Moon Papers
1976-2012
1991-2004
02/2016-006
Moon, Flora
6.00 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The majority of this collection contains documentation and notes pertaining to the creation of the short documentary film The Living Tree. Other items include film scripts, periodicals and ephemera from her film career.
Biographical Information:
Flora Moon is a film maker based in Los Angeles, Houston and Boston. Born in Indiana to Chinese immigrants Wei Ning and Tack-Shing Li, Flora knew very little about her Chinese roots growing up until her aunt De Ping moved to the United States in the 1980’s. She learned about her family’s recent history and how they were targeted during the Communist Revolution, as well as their ties to the Tang Dynasty. After visiting the People’s Republic of China and meeting her extended family, Flora created a short documentary film, The Living Tree about her journey discovering her Chinese roots. The majority of this collection contains correspondence, financial information, grant applications and proposals, historical and family research, production notes, audio-visual materials and books pertaining to the research and production of this documentary. Other items include film scripts, periodicals and ephemera from Flora Moon’s film career.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Correspondence; Photographs; Research (document genres); Videocassettes
Geographic Name:
China -- History
Topical Term:
Chinese Americans; Chinese diaspora
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
The majority of this collection contains documentation and notes pertaining to the creation of the short documentary film The Living Tree. Other items include film scripts, periodicals and ephemera from her film career.
Detailed List of Contents
- Contacts and Correspondence, id172621
  Scope and Contents
  Contact Lists and correspondence with Living Tree consultants, family in China and the United States, and correspondence with museums and archives regarding image rights for The Living Tree.
  - Contact Lists and Notes, undated; id172650 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Consultants – The Living Tree, 1992-1998, 2001-2004; id172651 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Family, 1978-96, undated; id172652 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Image Rights A-M, 1998, 2003-2005; id172653 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Image Rights M-S, 1991, 1993, 2003-2005; id172654 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Image Rights U-Z, 2003 -2004; id172655 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Workprint, 1978; id172656 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Financial Records, id172622
  Budgets, financing notes, receipts and other financial records related to the production of The Living Tree.
  - Budgets, 1994-2004; id172658 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Financing Notes, 1996-1998, undated; id172659 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - IRS Information, 1990-1994; id172660 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Receipts, 1992-2004, 2012; id172661 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Resumes Living Tree Contributors, undated; id172662 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Grant Applications, id172623
  Grant applications and responses, organized by funding organization.
  - Proposal Drafts, id172664 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Cultural Arts Council Houston and Harris County, 1997, undated; id172665 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - California Council for the Humanities, 1991-1995; id172666 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Corporation for Public Broadcasting, 1992, 1998; id172667 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Independent Television Service, 2004; id172668 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - National Endowment for the Arts, 1992-1995; id172669 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1994, undated; id172670 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - New York Council for the Humanities, 1995-1996, undated; id172671 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Texas Council for the Humanities Part 1, 1997-1998; id172673 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Texas Council for the Humanities Part 2, 1998-2004, undated; id172674 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Other Grant Applications, 1991, 1996-2000, 2004; id172675 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Research, id172624
  Research notes, images and materials related to the research and production of The Living Tree, including personal photos.
  - China before 618 AD, 2002-2004, undated; id172677 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Tang Dynasty (618-907), 2002 -2003, undated; id172678 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Song / Ming Era (1368-1644), 2003-2004, undated; id172679 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Qing Dynasty before Opium War (1644-1839), 2002-2004, undated; id172680 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Opium Wars (1839-1860), 1998, 2003-2004, undated; id172681 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Qing Dynasty after Opium War (1860-1911), 1998, 2003, undated; id172682 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Republic of China (1911-1949), 1998, 2003-2004, undated; id172683 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Mao Era (1949-1976), 1998, 2003-2004, undated; id172684 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - The Cold War Era in the US Part 1, 1950-1956, 1998; id172685 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - The Cold War Era in the U.S Part 2, 1998, 2000-2004, undated; id172686 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Modern China (1976-2016), 1992-1993, 1999, 2003-2004, undated; id172687 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Genealogy and Families, 1993-1994, 2004, undated; id172688 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Flora Moon Family, undated; id172689 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Interview Transcripts, 1992, undated; id172690 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Other Notes, 1989-1990, 2003, undated; id172691 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Production, id172625
  Production notes, rough cuts, script drafts, outlines and thumbnails for the production of the film The Living Tree.
  - Production Notes, undated; id172694 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Rough Cuts, undated; id172695 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Script Drafts and Outlines, 1986, 1992, 2004, undated; id172696 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Thumbnails, 1998; id172697 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Ephemera, id172626
  Issues of periodicals edited by or contributed to by Flora Moon, speeches, materials from the Where is Home? Conference, brochures and four scripts.
  - Amsterdam Weekly Issues, 2005; id172699 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Workprint Issues, 1976-1978; id172700 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Other Newsletters, 1982, 1992, 1994, 1997, undated; id172701 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Speeches, 1999; id172702 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Where Is Home? Conference Materials, 1997; id172703 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Ephemera, 1985, 1988-1989, 1993, 2000, undated; id172704 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - “Amazing Grace and Chuck” Script, 1986; id172705 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - “Concealed Enemies” Script, 1983; id172706 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - “The Dark End of the Street” Script, undated; id172707 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - “Haunted” Script, 1982; id172708 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Audiovisual and Digital Materials, id172627
  Tapes, discs and cassettes, mostly to do with the Living Tree.
  - VHS and Beta Tapes, id172709
    - American Express: Journey through China, undated; id172710 (Item 1)
    - Changing Our Minds: The Story of Dr. Evelyn Hooker, undated; id172711 (Item 2)
    - Cold War Era Footage for the Living Tree, undated; id172713 (Item 3)
    - Film History Foundation Footage Pull Reel Tape 1, undated; id172714 (Item 4)
    - Film History Foundation Footage Pull Reel Tape 2, undated; id172715 (Item 5)
    - KBYU’s Ancestor, undated; id172716 (Item 6)
    - Living Tree Demo Tape - VHS, undated; id172717 (Item 7)
    - Living Tree Demo Tape - Beta, undated; id172718 (Item 8)
    - Living Tree Excerpts: Imperial Family Tape 1, undated; id172719 (Item 9)
    - Living Tree Excerpts: Imperial Family Tape 2, undated; id172720 (Item 10)
    - Living Tree Film History Reels, undated; id172721 (Item 11)
    - The Living Tree Green Screen Tape 1, undated; id172722 (Item 12)
    - The Living Tree Green Screen Tape 2, undated; id172723 (Item 13)
    - The Living Tree Beta Tape 1, undated; id172724 (Item 14)
    - The Living Tree Beta Tape 2, undated; id172725 (Item 15)
    - The Living Tree DVD, undated; id172726 (Item 16)
    - The Living Tree VHS, undated; id172727 (Item 17)
    - The Living Tree Promo, undated; id172728 (Item 18)
    - Public Domain Footage, undated; id172729 (Item 19)
    - Phenomenology, undated; id172730 (Item 20)
    - Shanghai Film Studio, undated; id172731 (Item 21)
    - Special Dub for Moon Films, undated; id172732 (Item 22)
    - Westward to China, undated; id172733 (Item 23)
  - Discs, id172734
    - Bancroft Library Duplication Services, undated; id172735 (Item 24)
    - British Envoy in Beijing, undated; id172736 (Item 25)
    - British Library Reproductions Disc 1, undated; id172737 (Item 26)
    - British Library Reproductions Disc 2, undated; id172738 (Item 27)
    - Cartoon for the Living Tree, undated; id172739 (Item 28)
    - Creative Capital, undated; id172740 (Item 29)
    - Faust Copy 1, undated; id172741 (Item 30)
    - Faust Copy 2, undated; id172742 (Item 31)
    - Flora Moon, undated; id172743 (Item 32)
    - Flora A: Big Tree, undated; id172744 (Item 33)
    - Flora B: Love & Marriage, undated; id172745 (Item 34)
    - Flora C: L&M Movie, undated; id172746 (Item 35)
    - Garacci Photography & Digital Imaging, undated; id172747 (Item 36)
    - Imperial Tree, undated; id172748 (Item 37)
    - Luna 1, undated; id172749 (Item 38)
    - MFA Boston, undated; id172750 (Item 39)
    - MFA Images #1, undated; id172751 (Item 40)
    - National Anthropological Archives, undated; id172752 (Item 41)
    - Oakland Museum of California, undated; id172753 (Item 42)
    - Splendors of Imperial China, undated; id172754 (Item 43)
    - Tree ILN, undated; id172755 (Item 44)
    - Tree Script, undated; id172756 (Item 45)
    - Unlabeled 3.5” Removable Hard Disk Cartridge, undated; id172757 (Item 46)
    - Unlabeled Image Disk, undated; id172758 (Item 47)
    - Case containing 11 disks related to the Living Tree, undated; id172759 (Item 48)
  - DV Tapes, id172760
    - DV Master: The Living Tree, undated; id172761 (Item 49)
    - Family Tree, undated; id172762 (Item 50)
    - Half Hour Narrative, undated; id172763 (Item 51)
    - Tree, 04/23/04; id172764 (Item 52)
    - Tree VO Diverse Work Master, 12/28/99; id172765 (Item 53)
- Books, id172628
  Books used in the research and production of The Living Tree.
  - Abbate, Francesco Chinese Art 101 Full Color Illustrations, id172767 (Box 4, Item 1)
  - Birch, Cyril Stories From a Ming Collection: The Art of the Chinese Story-Teller, id172768 (Box 4, Item 2)
  - Chin, Frank et al., Aiiieeeee! An Anthology of Asian American Writers, id172769 (Box 4, Item 3)
  - Congressional Quarterly China U.S. Policy Since 1945, id172770 (Box 4, Item 4)
  - De Bary, Theodore Sources of Chinese Tradition Volume 1, id172771 (Box 4, Item 5)
  - De Bary, Theodore Sources of Chinese Tradition Volume 2, id172772 (Box 4, Item 6)
  - Durdin, T, et al., The New York Times report on Red China, id172773 (Box 4, Item 7)
  - Eberhard, Wolfram Folktales of China, id172774 (Box 4, Item 8)
  - Foreign Language Press The Magic Knife – Folk Tales from China (Fifth Series), id172775 (Box 4, Item 9)
  - Guanzhong, Luo Romance of the Three Kingdoms, id172776 (Box 4, Item 10)
  - Grathwol, Robert et al. Oral History and Postwar German-American Relations; Resources in the United States, id172777 (Box 4, Item 11)
  - Graubard, Stephen Daedalus Journal of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences 1991, id172778 (Box 4, Item 12)
  - Hawes, Dorothy Schurman To the Farthest Gulf: The Story of the American China Trade, id172779 (Box 4, Item 13)
  - Hu, Jason Chinese History in Brief, id172780 (Box 4, Item 14)
  - Isaacs, Harold R. Straw Sandals Chinese Short Stories, id172781 (Box 4, Item 15)
  - Jackson, Marcy The Grandparent Book, id172782 (Box 4, Item 16)
  - Legouix, Susan Image of China: William Alexander, id172783 (Box 4, Item 17)
  - Millar, Heather C hina’s Tang Dynasty, id172784 (Box 4, Item 18)
  - National Archives and Records Administration National Archives Records Relating to the Cold War, id172785 (Box 4, Item 19)
  - Nieh, Hualing Mulberry and Peach, id172786 (Box 4, Item 20)
  - Salisbury, Harrison The New Emperors, id172787 (Box 4, Item 21)
  - Smith, Richard China’s Cultural Heritage, id172788 (Box 4, Item 22)
  - Tan, Amy The Hundred Secret Senses, id172789 (Box 4, Item 23)
  - Tan, Thomas Tsu-wee Your Chinese Roots, id172791 (Box 5, Item 1)
  - Thomson, John China The Land its People, id172792 (Box 5, Item 2)
  - Tun, Mao Midnight, id172793 (Box 5, Item 3)
  - Van Over, Raymond A Treasury of Chinese Literature, id172794 (Box 5, Item 4)
  - Waley, Arthur Monkey Folk Novel of China, id172795 (Box 5, Item 5)
  - Waley, Arthur Three Ways of Thought in Ancient China, id172796 (Box 5, Item 6)
  - Waley, Arthur The Opium War Through Chinese Eyes, id172797 (Box 5, Item 7)
  - Westad et al., Cold War International History Project – 77 Conversations between Chinese and Foreign Leaders on the Wars in Indochina, id172798 (Box 5, Item 8)
  - Wolfman, Ira Do People Grow on Family Trees: Genealogy for Kids and Other Beginners, id172799 (Box 5, Item 9)
  - Xianyi, Yang Tang Dynasty Stories, id172800 (Box 5, Item 10)
  - Yutang, Lin The Vigil of a Nation, id172801 (Box 5, Item 11)
  - Zedong, Mao Lun Shi Da Guanxi (The Ten Relationships), id172802 (Box 5, Item 12)
  - Zeitlin, Steven et al. A Celebration of American Family Folklore, id172803 (Box 5, Item 13)
  - Unidentified Chinese Text, id172804 (Box 5, Item 14)
    (Chapters are Biography of Hang Yu, Lien Per and Lin Siang Ju, Tsu Yuan, Assassins)
  - Unidentified Chinese Text, id172805 (Box 5, Item 15)
    (Google Translate thinks the spine says Lin Chuan (popular edition) Susie Yong pose Taiwan Commercial Press Release – but searching revealed no results)